There's this huge new study that
released that indicates that UV light
like that from the sun is linked to
reduced risk of mortality. I was
contacted multiple times to cover it
because I had another analysis on
sunscreen that I recently did. So, here
I am reading this study and I can't help
it but laugh because there's so much
wrong here. It's flabbergasting. So, let
me walk you through the main findings
and then I'd like to point out some of
the issues and then broaden our scope to
other studies because as much as people
are making this out to be such a
impactful study, there's plenty of
others that look at the exact same
thing, UV and mortality in slightly
different ways. Now, I think we're
grossly misinterpreting what to take
away from this new analysis. I'm talking
about this study which is technically a
preprint so it hasn't undergone the peer
review process yet but since it was
uploaded to the interwebs the interwebs
are a buzz about it.
Do you hear it? Essentially they
measured the approximate exposure to
ultraviolet radiation UV radiation and
how many people died of any cause over
about 15 years. So then we can track low
exposure, moderate exposure, and high
exposure and compare how many people
died. And this was in a huge data set of
over 400,000 people. Pretty
straightforward. And here were the
results. That dotted line straight up
the middle is a neutral indication. So
no increased or reduced risk of death.
If the lines and dots move to the left,
there's reduced risk. And if they move
to the right, well, then there's
increased risk of death. We're seeing
two different comparisons for each
mortality type. High UV exposure versus
low low UV exposure and medium UV
exposure versus low UV exposure. Clearly
death from any cause, but also
cardiovascular disease related and even
cancer related death was reduced when
people were exposed to more UV light.
The big result of the study was that
although skin cancer mortality like
melanoma was increased with UV exposure,
all other major forms of mortality
including other cancers was diminished.
The even bigger point to emphasize is
that more people would be saved from
other forms of death than from skin
cancer related death. Clearly the risk
benefit changes in that context. Now,
another thing that this study did that
was unique is that they used a more
standardized criteria for assessing UV
exposure. It's called the sunbeam. What
a cute name. It looks like this. The
left side is the assessment criteria.
The more points that you accumulate, the
higher your UV exposure and therefore
your assignment to the high or moderate
UV groups. Remember, moderate and high
UV exposure was associated with reduced
overall mortality compared to low UV
exposure. Now, I'll inject a slightly
critical eye here in as my first
critique. There's two issues that I have
with this one. I'm not entirely sold on
how this section sun or UV protection is
being interpreted. Those given a point
for UV exposure are those protecting
their skin from the sun, which
technically means that they are exposing
to less UV radiation considering that
they're actively using sun protection,
which blocks UV radiation. On the flip
side, the zero condition there combines
those who don't go out in the sun. That
makes sense. But it also combined it
with those who never wear sun
protection, which would be the people
who would be exposed to the most UV
radiation when they do go outside. I
think the argument is that this speaks
to overall behavior, as in people who at
least sometimes wear sun protection are
generally people who seek out the sun
more often. Still, I think this is a bit
of an assumption and counterintuitive is
measured. To be fair, they designed
these criteria based on a grouping of
other studies and trying to standardize
the measures. I think it's a good idea
overall. But my second critique is
related to the binary measures, one or
zero. Should a single sunlamp use be
characterized as a full point compared
to someone who uses it 20 times? Or even
between categories? Time outdoors seems
like it should be weighted far higher
than sunlamp use. hand, keeping them on
the same playing field is like putting a
junior varsity team on an NFL field. On
the other hand, the more you segment the
data or as you apply weight to each
condition, it creates a lot more noise
and bias in interpreting the data. So, I
can really see both perspectives, but
these critiques are going to come back
later as we broaden the scope to other
studies as I promised. In fact, let's do
a bit of that now. While I've been
contacted about this study as if it's
the first study of its kind, and in some
small ways it is, there's actually many
studies that look at the relationship
between UV exposure and mortality. And
most of these studies agree ultraviolet
exposure is related to reduce risk of
all-c cause mortality. So across
multiple studies, we have an inverse
relationship. More ultraviolet light
exposure is related to reduced all-c
cause mortality, confirming our initial
study of interest. But just because I
say multiple studies agree does not mean
that all studies agree. In fact, I'm not
even talking about one study
disagreeing. I'm talking about many. We
can lean on a new systematic review like
this one that clearly outline how some
studies indicate benefit of UV exposure
and others do not. So, some actually
indicating the opposite. Now, I'm going
to enter a whole other level of
critique, which is my primary point, but
at the end of this, I promise to still
offer some actionable takeaways. I don't
want this to just be an intellectual
exercise. So, let me start out by asking
you, do you think that nutrition plays a
role in mortality?
Now, I certainly do. Yet, the
researchers don't account for nutrition.
They account for proxies like BMI and
alcohol consumption, which are good
controls, but they aren't expansive. In
fact, most of the studies on UV exposure
and mortality fail to account for
nutrition. But my point isn't about
nutrition specifically. It could be any
number of different factors that
contribute to mortality. This is what's
known as residual confounding, and it's
always present in these kinds of
associative studies. However, when
you're looking at more easily
controllable factors like nutrition,
physical activity, sleep, and so on, you
can account for common confounding
factors more easily. It's much more
difficult when you're trying to tease
out the effect of UV light because
there's many factors that also need to
be accounted for which aren't. This is
critically important because as the
paper is written and the way it's
discussed and even the title is focused
on ultraviolet light and reduce
mortality yet we are not actually
measuring the strict exposure to UV
light are we? Let me ask you what else
are we measuring if we're measuring the
exposure to the sun. Yes, UV light is
one, but visible light is a huge portion
and infrared light is another massive
portion. So why are we so focused on UV
light and extolling the potential
benefits of UV light yet ignoring the
bigger players in the room? That's
equivalent to looking at the consumption
of carbohydrates and pinning the
benefits on glucose while not
acknowledging fiber was also consumed.
Okay, I'm about to strengthen my
argument even further and I'll mention
really quickly that I'm doing a longer
analysis of this study for my premium
research review called the Physionic
Insiders. I'll be getting into some of
the even nerdier details. Now, if you
care to join, you'll also get an
accompanying article and all these perks
right here, and you can discuss it in
the insider community with me if you're
interested. Anyway, link to join is in
the description box. Before I get into
strengthening my point, I realize that
you may not be interested. So, skip to
this timestamp to a point where I've
babbled myself out and I'll put my main
takeaways together for you. So, my first
point is that we have a growing body of
literature indicating that benefits of
infrared light. Now, I've covered some
of that in the past. To be fair, there
are some studies using UV light as well
that indicate benefits like reduce blood
pressure from direct exposure. However,
when we look at animal studies, a type
of study that we can't do in humans, and
we expose them to UV continuously for 2
hours, 4 hours, or 6 hours, the animals
die at an astounding rate. The higher
the lines remain, the better the
survival. The top line is the control.
So no heavy UV exposure. As you can see,
UV exposure at any amount leads to
devastating mortality effects. Now this
is in a lower life form. Sea elegance
worms. And for anyone not in the field
of biomedical research, you'll scoff.
But without getting into an education on
why sea elegance research is important,
I'll just say that many of the DNA
repair mechanisms are conserved between
these animals and humans. Is this
definitive proof? Absolutely not. But it
does fall in line with plenty of other
research, including in humans,
indicating harm of UV radiation, even if
there's also some evidence for benefits.
My point here isn't to offer certainty,
but to actually do the opposite, to
introduce uncertainty with how we
discuss UV exposure and mortality. My
second point bolsters the first. If we
look at the studies that do adjust for
nutrition, there's a particular study
that separates UV exposure by the sun
and UV exposure by salarium use. Let me
pause here and ask you, sorry about all
the questions, but this one is
important. When you hear the term or the
word salarium, what comes to mind
immediately? And I'm asking because
these studies use the word without
properly defining it. If you look it up,
it's a sun room. Or by other
definitions, it's a sunlight. Or by
others, it's a UV tanning bed. It's
frustrating when the definition isn't
provided because it changes the analysis
drastically. In fact, the main study
that we've been focused on combined
salarium with sunlamp. Anyway, in this
study, they use the term interchangeably
with artificial UV exposure, which I
assume is a tanning bed. That's
critically important because when people
use a tanning bed on a regular basis,
one time per month or more, there is an
increased risk of mortality. In the same
study, they show a reduced risk of
mortality when exposed to more sun.
This goes exactly to my point. Since UV
tanning beds do not usually include
infrared light or at least massively
overindex on UV light, yet sunlight
massively overindexes on infrared light,
not UV light. So this would speak to the
benefit of red and infrared light but
not UV exposure. To be clear, we don't
have enough granularity here to state
that as a fact, but it's definitely a
possibility. Then, as a final critique
before I shut up and give you the
actionable takeaways, this systematic
review that recently released included
55 studies on UV exposure and mortality.
Across all 55 studies, not a single
study was labeled as low risk of bias,
meaning that every study had some form
of inherent potential bias with the two
most prevalent being uncontrolled
confounding. So what I mentioned earlier
about residual confounding factors that
could explain the outcome aside from
what's being measured like UV exposure
and the second being a huge risk of bias
is how the UV exposure was measured.
It's usually though not always through
estimates from where a person lives. So
like the northern hemisphere for
example. Okay, let me pull us out of the
weeds. I usually avoid this level of
detail except in my insider analysis
simply because they get a bit
overwhelming. What do we make of all
these data? Well, putting aside the
gaping holes in the data that still need
to be addressed. Nothing that I've said
up to now is an argument to avoid sun.
The main argument is that we are
misinterpreting or misrepresenting what
the data is indicating by focusing on UV
exposure and discussing it as a quasi
causal factor for reduced mortality. It
is entirely possible and maybe even
likely that the real relationship is
between infrared light exposure and
reduced mortality and we're just
measuring UV exposure or considering
that the holes in the evidence that
something else is the true cause of this
relationship independent of light
wavelength exposure. Here's how I'd
approach this based on what we do have.
Don't avoid the sun. There's plenty of
benefits, but I would still make sure to
try to block UV exposure until we have
better evidence that UV is the real
causal factor. Sunscreen, if you didn't
know, only blocks UV. It does not block
other wavelengths like infrared. So, you
can get the best of both worlds without
worry. Sorry for the technical nature of
this video. I would actually have much
more to say, but I have to balance
length, yawn rate, and accuracy when I'm
creating these. In fact, if you want
more on sunlight, then check out this
video right here. I promise it's less
dense. Thanks for tuning in. I
appreciate it, and I'll catch you in the
next one. Bye.